AFT Local 616 (Rochester, NY) Federation of Classroom Teachers Records 5845
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
AFT Local 616 (Rochester, NY) Federation of Classroom Teachers Records
1929-1971
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Federation of Teachers (AFT)
AFT Local 616
Federation of Classroom Teachers
5845
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
5713663
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 07, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 17, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The American Federation of Teachers (AFT) was started in Chicago, with eight locals signing on as AFL president Samuel Gompers welcomed the union into its fold in 1916.
AFT grew quickly in the beginning, chartering 174 locals in its first four years. The years following World War I saw school boards pressuring and intimidating teachers to resign from the union.
As membership dropped in the 1920s, the union continued to fight for tenure laws and academic freedom of the teachers whose beliefs were being investigated by political committees during the 'Red scare" hysteria following WWI.
The Depression years were not much better, low salaries and economic insecurity were issues needing attention. Female teachers found themselves faced with "contracts which still stipulated that an employed teacher must wear skirts of certain lengths, keep her galoshes buckled, not receive gentleman callers more than three times a week and teach a Sunday School class," said the American Teacher magazine. In some cases teachers were dismissed for joining the AFT or for working on school board election campaigns.
By 1932, the Norris-La Guardia Act outlawed yellow dog contracts, which made teachers promise not to join the union.
Starting with WWII the AFT worked hard to push war bond sales, war relief and air raid programs in schools. After the war the AFT continued to fight to improve the conditions of the schools and their teachers.
In the 1950s, loyalty oaths started up again. The AFT continued work on the civil rights movement, filing an amicus curiae brief in the historic 1954 Supreme Court desegregation case Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, and expelling locals that had not followed an earlier mandate to desegregate.
During the 1960s, besides fighting for civil rights, the AFT and its affiliates worked at getting collective bargaining agreements with stubborn school boards. Also the first major strike by university professors in the United States and a one-day walkout by the United Federation of Teachers in New York City took place. Over 300 teacher strikes occurred throughout the country during the 10 years following the UFT's walkout. The national AFT grew from less than 60,000 members in 1960 to over 200,000 by the end of the decade.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- Rochester; American Federation of Teachers.; American Federation of Teachers. Local 616 (Rochester, N.Y.)
5713663
- Mail Box Policy, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - General, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Briggs - Subcommittee 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence Misc., 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Coaches 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence AFT, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Boycott, March 3, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Monroe Com. St. John's, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Alinsky, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- N.Y. City UFT, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1964 - Election, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Agenda 70-71 + Minutes 70-71, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- New Caucus, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Biernbaum, Brown, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence Board of Educ., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence ESFT, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- I #29, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Salding Class, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 5% TakeHome, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence Retirement, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- ME - Correspondence - Releases positions, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- RFCT - Newspaper, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Federation (Box 1, Folder 25)
- RFCT - Members (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Longer School Day, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Vocational Ed., 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Release - Statements, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Issues, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Organizing AID from Union Brothers, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- ESFT Organization 1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- B. of Education Minutes, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Election Results 1964 and Negotiations Dec 2, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Union - Pres McKensie, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Commissioner Allen, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Rochester - Desegregation 3 -'67, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Richard Bouchard, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Scope and Contents
  2 Photographs
- Anne Browne et al. CF Birnebaum Letters, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Budget, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- RFCT - Conferences, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Retirement General, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Conf. + Programs, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Tenure, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Communications - AFT - Dir. Organization, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- I.U.D. Materials, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Salary Matters Local, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- B. Of Education Presentations, 1929-1945 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Clipping, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- ESFT - Newspaper UFT, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)